<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>There Is Always a Reason…</title>
    <link href="https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com" />
    <updated>2025-06-13T06:37:19+12:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Maria Vernon</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Hitting</title>
        <author>
            <name>Maria Vernon</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/hitting.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/hitting.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/media/posts/9/Hitting-1000px.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="Sample Chapters"/>

        <updated>2025-06-13T06:32:02+12:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/media/posts/9/Hitting-1000px.jpg" alt="Pencil sketch of angry boy with fist raised as if to hit" />
                    No, It’s Not Caused by Bad Parenting! Few things make parents question themselves quicker than discovering their toddler has hit someone. But before you start envisioning a future of thuggery, pause a moment. Hitting among preschoolers is not a reflection of bad parenting or genetics.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/media/posts/9/Hitting-1000px.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Pencil sketch of angry boy with fist raised as if to hit" /></p>
                <h3 class="p1"><i>No, It’s Not Caused by Bad Parenting!</i></h3>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">F</span>ew things make parents question themselves quicker than discovering their toddler has hit someone. But before you start envisioning a future of thuggery, pause a moment. Hitting among preschoolers is not a reflection of bad parenting or genetics. It’s quite common behavior.</p>
<h4 class="p2"><strong>There Is Always a Reason:</strong></h4>
<p class="p1"><span class="s2">Put simply, hitting arises from frustration, lack of impulse control, and a toddlers’ limited ability to express their needs in words.</span></p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Toddlers are still learning self-control: </strong>They get frustrated, overwhelmed, or really mad, and they often lack the ability to pause and think before reacting (remind you of road rage?).</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• They rely on actions, not words: </strong>If sharing isn’t going their way or another child is too close, their instinct might be to push or hit.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Impulse control develops over time: </strong>Typically, later than we wish! Expecting a preschooler to manage frustration without physical reactions is like expecting a puppy to stop chewing shoes just because you asked politely.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• They’re testing boundaries: </strong>A reaction means they’re learning about limits, emotions, and what happens when impulses take over.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• They’re saying hello: </strong>Surprisingly, some children hit simply to get attention—from both adults and other children. It’s their way of saying, “I’m here!”</p>
<h4 class="p2"><strong>Here's What I've Found Works:</strong></h4>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Stay calm: </strong>If your child is lashing out, the last thing they need is for you to escalate the situation with your frustration. They need guidance, not intensity.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Look for triggers: Ask yourself:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li class="p5">Where does the behavior happen?</li>
<li class="p5">What happened right before?</li>
<li class="p5">Is the environment overstimulating or chaotic?</li>
<li class="p5">Are there patterns with specific people or settings?</li>
</ul>
<p class="p6">Finding patterns helps you understand (and prevent) future outbursts.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Model positive responses: </strong>Instead of forcing an insincere “sorry,” try narrating the situation: “You really wanted that truck, but hitting hurts. Let’s check if they’re okay.” Teaching empathy through actions works better than insisting on empty words.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Help them find the words: </strong><span class="s2">Encourage alternatives: “When you’re mad, say ‘I’m mad!’ instead of hitting.” They won’t always remember, but the more you reinforce it, the sooner it will click.</span></p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Be consistent: </strong>If hitting happens, remove them from the situation and explain: “I can’t let you hurt others. You can take a break until you’re ready to be gentle.” This isn’t punishment, but a moment to reset.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Teach physical alternatives: </strong>Some children genuinely need physical outlets. Offer stress balls, tight hugs, or stomping as ways to release frustration without hurting others. Outdoor play (or maybe a punching bag?) is also great for calming some children down.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Ensure adequate sleep and nutrition: </strong>Overtired or hungry children have much lower frustration tolerance and impulse control. Sticking to consistent sleep schedules and offering regular, healthy meals/snacks can significantly reduce hitting triggered by physical discomfort.</p>
<h4 class="p2"><strong>Common Challenges:</strong></h4>
<p class="p3"><strong>• They hit again moments later: </strong>Learning self-control takes time. Keep reinforcing boundaries and don’t expect instant results.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• They don’t seem to care that they hurt someone: </strong>Empathy is learned through experience. Keep modeling it—eventually, it will sink in.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• They hit when they’re excited, not just angry: </strong>Some children hit when overstimulated. Help them find calmer ways to engage or take a break.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• They laugh when you correct them: </strong>This isn’t defiance—it’s often nervousness or discomfort. Keep your tone steady and clear, and don’t take the giggles personally.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Hitting is directed primarily at one person: </strong>If the hitting seems targeted rather than random frustration, look for triggers. <span class="s2">What happened just before the hitting? Is there a pattern of provocation (even unintentional)?</span> Once you know what the trigger is, you can address it.</p>
<h4 class="p2"><strong>Look on the Bright Side</strong></h4>
<p class="p1">Hitting is common and developmentally very typical during the toddler and preschool years. Young children don’t yet have the tools to manage big emotions or social situations, so they often express themselves through action. This doesn’t mean you should ignore it. It means you should approach it calmly, consistently, and with understanding. Hitting isn’t a sign of bad parenting or a bad child; it’s a sign that your child is still learning how to navigate their big feelings.</p>
<p class="p7">●●●</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Anger</title>
        <author>
            <name>Maria Vernon</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/post-2.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/post-2.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/media/posts/4/Anger-300.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="Sample Chapters"/>

        <updated>2025-06-12T11:12:00+12:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/media/posts/4/Anger-300.png" alt="" />
                    No One Gets Angry for No Reason. Anger is a normal part of all our lives—and of course, that includes the life of your preschooler. It can be hard to watch, especially when the outbursts are loud, messy, and (most embarrassingly) public. It falls to&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/media/posts/4/Anger-300.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <h3 class="p1"><i>No One Gets Angry for No Reason.</i></h3>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">A</span>nger is a normal part of all our lives—and of course, that includes the life of your preschooler. It can be hard to watch, especially when the outbursts are loud, messy, and (most embarrassingly) public. It falls to you to help your child learn to handle their anger in a way that doesn’t involve throwing toys or screaming so loudly that the neighbors can hear.</p>
<h4 class="p2"><strong>There Is Always a Reason:</strong></h4>
<p class="p1">Your child’s brain isn’t fully developed, which means their impulse control is still a work in progress. When frustration and disappointment hit, they don’t have the ability to manage it the way adults do. They’re not deliberately trying to push your buttons—<strong>they’re overwhelmed and don’t know what else to do.</strong></p>
<h4 class="p2"><strong>Here’s What I've Found Works:</strong></h4>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Stay calm yourself: </strong><span class="s2">Your child looks to you to see how you handle your emotions. If you can keep your cool, they’ll eventually learn to do the same. Here’s my own mantra: “They’re not giving me a hard time; they’re having a hard time.” This conscious shift in perspective makes a big difference when faced with your child’s anger (it did for me).</span></p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Let them be angry: </strong>It may feel counterintuitive, but sometimes the best response is to let the emotions run their course. Nobody likes being told to “calm down” when they’re upset.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Now’s not the time: </strong>While they’re angry isn’t the time for big life lessons, or to be told to “calm down”. When emotions are running high, reasoning with your preschooler is about as effective as explaining bitcoin to a goldfish! A simple nod or just being nearby is the best support.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Keep everyone safe: </strong>Anger is one thing, but hitting, throwing, or physically lashing out is obviously another. You don’t need to be told to gently intervene to keep your child (and others) safe. Just be careful not to shame them for their emotions.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Talk about it later (much later): </strong>When your child is completely calm (a few hours later, or even the next day), briefly revisit the incident. “Remember when you got mad earlier? What could we do differently next time?” Focus on solutions, not blame.</p>
<p class="p3"><strong>• Model healthy anger management: </strong>When you’re upset, try talking about your own process. “I’m feeling frustrated right now, so I’m going to take five deep breaths before we talk about this.”</p>
<h4 class="p1"><strong>Common Challenges:</strong></h4>
<p class="p2"><strong>• You want to “fix” it instantly: </strong>It’s natural to want to snuff out the anger quickly, but trying to do so will likely escalate things. Give them space to express their feelings first.</p>
<p class="p2"><strong>• Ongoing angry outbursts: </strong>If anger keeps happening, step back and look for patterns. Are they overtired, hungry, or overwhelmed? Addressing root causes works wonders. In my professional life, I’d keep records of what led up to children showing anger regularly—that way I could begin to identify their triggers.</p>
<p class="p2"><strong>• Public settings feel mortifying (for you!): </strong>Handling intense anger is tough anywhere, but it feels a lot harder in the supermarket aisle with strangers watching (or seeming to watch). The pressure to control your child quickly can derail your best intentions. If it’s all too much, find somewhere quiet for both of you to reset.</p>
<p class="p2"><strong>• Your own triggers show up: </strong>Your child’s intense emotions can understandably trigger your own frustration or anger, making it hard to respond calmly. Try self-calming techniques (deep breaths, counting, repeating the mantra above). If possible and safe, take a brief moment for yourself (even just turning away for a few seconds) before responding.</p>
<p class="p2"><strong>• Inconsistency between caregivers: </strong>Different parents, grandparents, or caregivers might have different approaches to handling anger, confusing your child. Talk with other regular caregivers about your strategies to get a generally consistent approach.</p>
<h4 class="p1"><strong>Look on the Bright Side</strong></h4>
<p class="p4">Anger is one of those emotions we all wish our children could just… skip. Few things test your patience like a preschooler’s full-volume outburst in the middle of the mall. But anger is something your child is still learning to navigate.</p>
<p class="p4">Their angry outbursts aren’t intentional misbehavior; they’re raw expressions of feelings that are too big for their current skill set. They’re struggling with overwhelming feelings that they lack the vocabulary and experience to process. When they lose control with you, it’s a sign that they feel safe enough to show their real emotions.</p>
<p class="p4">With your calm support and steady presence, your child will gradually learn how to recognize, express, and manage their anger in healthier ways. Emotional regulation doesn’t happen all at once—it’s something they grow into as they consistently feel understood and supported.</p>
<p class="p4">You won’t always handle it perfectly, and you don’t need to. Just remember, anger always has a trigger, even when it’s not immediately obvious.</p>
<p class="p4">No one gets angry for no reason!</p>
<p class="p4">Look for that trigger.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>After-Daycare Meltdowns</title>
        <author>
            <name>Maria Vernon</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/after-daycare-meltdowns.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/after-daycare-meltdowns.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/media/posts/3/After-Daycare-Meltdowns-300.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="Sample Chapters"/>

        <updated>2025-06-10T09:37:59+12:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/media/posts/3/After-Daycare-Meltdowns-300.png" alt="" />
                    It’s REALLY Hard Being Good All Day. You pick up your child from daycare (or a playdate) expecting cheerful chatter about their day. Instead, you get whining, tears, or a full-blown collapse! If this sounds familiar, the good news is that your child isn’t the&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thereisalwaysareason.com/media/posts/3/After-Daycare-Meltdowns-300.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <h3 class="p1"><i>It’s REALLY Hard Being Good All Day.</i></h3>
<p class="p1"><span class="s1">Y</span>ou pick up your child from daycare (or a playdate) expecting cheerful chatter about their day. Instead, you get whining, tears, or a full-blown collapse! If this sounds familiar, the good news is that your child isn’t the only one who does this.</p>
<p class="p1">The even better news?</p>
<p class="p1">It’s completely normal.</p>
<h4 class="p2"><strong>There Is Always a Reason:</strong></h4>
<p class="p1">Your child has spent their entire day working hard at something adults often take for granted—emotional regulation. They’ve been:</p>
<ul>
<li class="p3">Holding back tears when frustrated.</li>
<li class="p3">Following rules (even when they didn’t want to).</li>
<li class="p3">Sharing toys, waiting for their turn, and generally keeping it together.</li>
</ul>
<p class="p1">Daycare is fun, but for them, it’s also work. Hard work.</p>
<p class="p1">When they see you, they feel emotionally safe; the mask comes off and they let it all out.</p>
<p class="p1">This makes you the privileged person who has their trust.</p>
<h4 class="p2"><strong>Here's What I've Found Works:</strong></h4>
<p class="p4"><strong>• Food: </strong>A hungry child is a cranky child. Stave off the meltdown with a car snack for the road.</p>
<p class="p4"><strong>• Be patient: </strong>Your calm presence helps them feel safe as they process the overwhelm of their day.</p>
<p class="p4"><strong>• Allow decompression: </strong>Some children need cuddles, while others may prefer quiet time. Give them space to unwind in their own way.</p>
<p class="p4"><strong>• Offer calming activities: </strong>Easy, low-energy activities help reset emotions. Consider drawing, puzzles, or coloring. Outdoor time—like soothing water play or even jumping in puddles on wet days—is calming.</p>
<p class="p4"><strong>• Establish a predictable after-daycare routine: </strong>A special greeting, a favorite song or story in the car, or a specific order of activities when you get home. A familiar sequence of events will help your child make a smoother transition from daycare to home.</p>
<p class="p4"><strong>• Consider break days: </strong>If your child is exhausted from daycare, an occasional break day can help.</p>
<h4 class="p2"><strong>Common Challenges:</strong></h4>
<p class="p4"><strong>• You want your child to be happy to see you: </strong>They are! But after a long day of holding in emotions, they need to let those feelings out. Don’t take it personally!</p>
<p class="p4"><strong>• You’re looking forward to hearing about their day: </strong>Accept that they won’t tell you during a meltdown. Instead, focus on that crumpled picture they drew for you (you’ll find it at the bottom of their bag!).</p>
<p class="p4"><strong>• You worry they’re not happy at their daycare: </strong>While it’s good to stay aware, most after-daycare meltdowns stem from emotional exhaustion, not problems at their center (but check with their teachers if you’re really concerned).</p>
<p class="p4"><strong>• You want your own after-work meltdown: </strong>Find time for yourself first (and maybe a little screen time for them?). Then do something together—outside is always a good option.</p>
<p class="p4"><strong>• Everything you do is wrong: </strong>The snack is wrong. The seatbelt is wrong. Even how you opened the door is wrong! Of course, it’s not really about those things—it’s classic after-daycare meltdown time. Stay calm, offer choices when possible, and give them time to unwind.</p>
<p class="p2"><strong>Look on the Bright Side</strong></p>
<p class="p1">It can feel confusing, even a little hurtful, when your child behaves beautifully all day for others, only to fall apart when they see you. However, it’s not a sign anything is wrong—with them or with you. It’s evidence that they trust you enough to let their guard down.</p>
<p class="p1">Their meltdown isn’t a rejection of you; it’s a powerful sign of trust. Your child has been working hard all day to hold it together and seeing you—their safe person—gives them permission to let their real feelings out.</p>
<p class="p1">This stage won’t last forever. With gentle routines, time to decompress, and your steady support, your child will gradually learn to manage the overwhelming feelings that come at the end of a busy day.</p>
<p class="p1">Your calm presence after a hard day means everything to them.</p>
<p class="p1">You’re their safe harbor.</p>
<p class="p1">After-daycare meltdowns are a stage.</p>
<p class="p1">They are very normal.</p>
<p class="p6"> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
